The Five Heartbeats is a drama, music film directed by Robert Townsend.
In the early 1960s, a quintet of hopeful, young African-American men
form an amateur vocal group called The Five Heartbeats.
After an initially rocky start, the group improves, turns pro,
and rises to become a top flight music sensation.
Along the way, however, the guys learn many hard lessons
about the reality of the music industry.
Duck, played by Robert Townsend.
Eddie, played by Michael Wright.
J.T., played by Leon.
Dresser, played by Harry Lennix.
Choirboy, played by Tico Wells.
Eleanor Potter, played by Diahann Carroll.
The Five Heartbeats is a 1991 musical drama film directed by Robert
Townsend, who co-wrote the script with Keenen Ivory Wayans.
Produced and distributed by 20th Century Fox, the film's main cast
includes Townsend, Michael Wright, Leon Robinson, Harry J.
Lennix, Tico Wells, John Canada Terrell, Harold Nicholas, and Diahann Carroll.
The plot of the film (which is loosely based on the lives of several artists: The Dells, The Temptations, Four Tops, Wilson Pickett, James
Brown, Frankie Lymon, Sam Cooke and others) follows the three decade career of the rhythm and blues vocal group The Five Heartbeats.
The film depicts the rise and fall of a Motown-inspired soul act through
the eyes of one of the Heartbeats, Donald "Duck" Matthews.
The film was released to most North American audiences on March 29, 1991; however, it was not made
available to audiences in other continents until 2002, when a DVD was released.
Another DVD was released in 2006 for the film's 15th anniversary.
Even though the movie received mixed reviews from critics at the time of its release, it became a
cult classic through VHS rentals, with many calling it Townsend's masterpiece.
The film explores themes of rhythm and blues (r&b), battle of the bands, 1960s.
The tone is uplifting and emotional.